Database

Setting up Oracle Database 12c.

Create Schema

In SQLPLUS, run command alter session set "_ORACLE_SCRIPT"
Create a new user:

                CREATE USER DEMO
                IDENTIFIED BY password1
                DEFAULT TABLESPACE users
                TEMPORARY TABLESPACE temp
                QUOTA 20M on users;
                

Grant privileges:

                GRANT create session TO demo;
                GRANT create table TO demo;
                GRANT create view TO demo;
                GRANT create any trigger TO demo;
                GRANT create any procedure TO demo;
                GRANT create sequence TO demo;
                GRANT create synonym TO demo;
                

Create schema:

                CREATE SCHEMA AUTHORIZATION demo;
                    CREATE TABLE products
                       ( product_id number(10) not null,
                         product_name varchar2(50) not null,
                         category varchar2(50),
                         CONSTRAINT products_pk PRIMARY KEY (product_id)
                        );
                

Change what schema you're in with:

                 ALTER SESSION SET CURRENT_SCHEMA=DEMO;  
                

And make a synonym for your table:

                CREATE PUBLIC SYNONYM products
                    FOR demo.products;
                

Note: Working with tables in SQL Plus is annoying, so connect with SQL Developer instead.

Connecting Oracle DB to NetBeans

Next, connect NetBeans to the DB. Use Oracle Thin client driver, which can be downloaded at the link in the wizard. In customize connection, choose:

Driver name: Oracle Thin SID
Host: localhost, port: 1521
Service ID: orcl
Username: demo
Password: password1

Then test the connection.

Setting up persistence

You'll need to start a project before this next step.

In NetBeans, go to file -> new file and search persistence to locate "persistence unit". Use your local DB address as the connection, e.g. demo@//localhost:1521/orcl.
Log into Admin Console and configure the data source under Services -> Data Sources -> New. Use the database name, host name, port, username and password you used during the database setup. Test the configuration and finish. NOTE: Make sure "AdminServer" (or whatever you named your server) is selected as a target.

Login

None :) package Bean; import java.io.Serializable; import java.util.logging.Level; import java.util.logging.Logger; import javax.enterprise.inject.Model; import javax.faces.context.ExternalContext; import javax.faces.context.FacesContext; import javax.servlet.ServletException; import javax.servlet.http.HttpServletRequest; /** * Handles logic for logging in and out. */ @Model public class LoginBean implements Serializable { private static final long serialVersionUID = 1L; private static final Logger LOG = Logger.getLogger(LoginBean.class.getName()); private boolean flag = false; private String username = null; private String password = null; /** * Log user in if they are in the appropriate role. * Otherwise, throw an error. * * @return The correct URL String based on whether * or not the user is in the right role. */ public String login() { ExternalContext ec = FacesContext.getCurrentInstance() .getExternalContext(); HttpServletRequest req = (HttpServletRequest) ec.getRequest(); try { req.login(username,password); if(req.isUserInRole("Admin")) { flag=true; return "Admin/AdminPage.xhtml? faces-redirect=true"; } else { System.out.println("User not in role!"); return null; } } catch (ServletException se) { System.out.println("Bad username or password"); return null; } } /** * Log user out. * * @return A URL String redirecting to the correct * page if the logout is successful, otherwise * throw an error. */ public String logout() { ExternalContext ec = FacesContext.getCurrentInstance() .getExternalContext(); HttpServletRequest req = (HttpServletRequest) ec.getRequest(); try { req.logout(); ec.invalidateSession(); ec.redirect(ec.getRequestContextPath() + "/Login.xhtml?faces-redirect=true"); return ""; } catch (Exception e) { LOG.log(Level.INFO, "Logout failed"); return null; } } /** * Check whether user is logged in. * * @return The status of the boolean flag - * true if user is logged in, false otherwise. */ public boolean getFlag() { return flag; } /** * Set the flag indicating if a user is * logged in or out. * * @param flag Set true if the user is logged in, * else set false. */ public void setFlag(boolean flag) { this.flag = flag; } /* Getters and Setters */ public String getUsername() { return username; } public void setUsername(String username) { this.username = username; } public String getPassword() { return password; } public void setPassword(String password) { this.password = password; } }

Search

Coffee Name #{coffee.variety} View More Edit No Results <?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' ?> <!DOCTYPE composition PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd"> <ui:composition template="./WEB-INF/templates/template.xhtml" xmlns:ui="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/facelets" xmlns:f="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/core" xmlns:h="http://xmlns.jcp.org/jsf/html" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> <f:metadata> <f:viewParam name='searchString' value='#{searchBean.searchQuery}'/> </f:metadata> <ui:define name="content"> <!--The search bar--> <h1>Search</h1> <h:form> <div class="input-group"> <h:inputText class="form-control" value="#{searchBean.searchQuery}"></h:inputText> <span class="input-group-btn"> <h:commandButton class="btn btn-default" value="Search" action="#{searchBean.displaySearch()}"/> </span> </div> </h:form> <!--The results--> <h:dataTable class="table" value="#{searchBean.results}" var="coffee" rendered="#{not empty searchBean.results}"> <h:column> <f:facet name="header">Coffee Name</f:facet> #{coffee.variety} </h:column> <h:column> <f:facet name="header">View More</f:facet> <h:button outcome="ViewCoffee?id=#{coffee.id}" value="Go"/> </h:column> <h:column> <f:facet name="header">Edit</f:facet> <h:button outcome="EditCoffee?id=#{coffee.id}" value="Go"/> </h:column> </h:dataTable> <h:column rendered="#{empty searchBean.results and searchBean.searchQuery ne null}"> <strong>No Results</strong> </h:column> </ui:define> </ui:composition> package Service; import Pojo.Coffee; import java.util.List; import javax.ejb.Stateless; import javax.persistence.EntityManager; import javax.persistence.PersistenceContext; import javax.persistence.Query; /** * Handles connection to Coffee table. */ @Stateless public class CoffeeService { @PersistenceContext(unitName="InstantCoffeePU") private EntityManager em; /** * Load a Coffee object given an ID. * * @param id Identifier for the Coffee object to load. * @return Coffee object associated with the ID. */ public Coffee load(Long id) { return em.find(Coffee.class, id); } /** * Add a new Coffee object to the database. * * @param coffee The new Coffee object to be persisted. */ public void create(Coffee coffee) { em.persist(coffee); } /** * Get all Coffee objects in the database. * * @return A List containing all Coffee * objects in the database. */ public List<Coffee> findAll() { Query q = em.createNamedQuery("Coffee.FindAll"); List<Coffee> coffees = (List<Coffee>) q.getResultList(); return coffees; } /** * Update a Coffee object in the database. * * @param coffee The Coffee object being updated. */ public void update(Coffee coffee) { em.merge(coffee); } /** * Query the Coffee table based on a search string. * * @param searchString The search text to query by. * @return A List of Coffee objects matching the search. */ public List<Coffee> searchByAll(String searchString) { Query q = em.createNamedQuery("Coffee.findByAll"); // Note: This must match the name given // in the view's viewparam. q.setParameter("searchString", ("%"+searchString+"%").toLowerCase()); List<Coffee> coffees = (List<Coffee>) q.getResultList(); return coffees; } /** * Delete a Coffee object from the table. * * @param coffee Coffee to delete. */ public void delete(Coffee coffee) { em.merge(coffee); em.remove(coffee); } } package Bean; import Pojo.Coffee; import Service.CoffeeService; import java.util.ArrayList; import java.util.Arrays; import java.util.List; import java.util.logging.Level; import java.util.logging.Logger; import javax.annotation.PostConstruct; import javax.ejb.EJB; import javax.faces.bean.ManagedBean; import javax.faces.bean.RequestScoped; /** * Handles searching the database and presenting results. */ @ManagedBean @RequestScoped public class SearchBean { private static final long serialVersionUID = 1L; private static final Logger LOG = Logger.getLogger(ViewCoffeeBean.class.getName()); @EJB private CoffeeService coffeeService; private String searchQuery; private List<Coffee> results = new ArrayList<>(); /** * Init method. */ @PostConstruct public void init() { } /** * Display the results of a given search query. */ public void displaySearch() { results.clear(); for (String str : stringHandler(searchQuery)) { searchCoffees(str); } } /** * Perform a search of the Coffee database table * based on the given search String(s), and add * the results to a List. * * @param str The search string. */ public void searchCoffees(String str) { List<Coffee> coffees = coffeeService.searchByAll(str); try { for (Coffee i : coffees) { results.add(i); } } catch (Exception e) { LOG.log(Level.INFO, "Error performing search", e); } } /** * Split apart a search query into individuals * strings, and handle empty search queries. * * @param str The search query entered in the * search bar. * @return A List of Strings representing the * parts of the search. */ public List<String> stringHandler(String str) { List<String> searchTerms = new ArrayList<>(); try { if (str != null && !str.isEmpty()) { searchTerms.addAll( Arrays.asList(str.split(" "))); } } catch (Exception e) { LOG.log(Level.INFO, "Null search term", e); } return searchTerms; } /* Getters and Setters */ public CoffeeService getCoffeeService() { return coffeeService; } public String getSearchQuery() { return searchQuery; } public void setSearchQuery(String searchQuery) { this.searchQuery = searchQuery; } public List<Coffee> getResults() { return results; } public void setResults(List<Coffee> results) { this.results = results; } }

Setup

Configuring your system for Java EE.

Install JDK

Setup JAVA_HOME in Windows. Follow the steps laid out here. Note that you should use an absolute path name to your Java installation, e.g. C:\Program Files\Java\jdk1.8.0_144. Use JAVA_HOME\bin in your Path. Note: if this doesn't work, look at the directory C:\ProgramData\Oracle\Java\javapath. If there are symbolic links in here that point to the wrong Java version (e.g. Java 7), they may need to be deleted.

Install Oracle WebLogic Server 12c

Launch the command prompt as administrator. Navigate to the location where you extracted the WebLogic Server files.
Type java -jar fmw_12.2.1.3.0_wls_quick.jar (or whatever version number of WebLogic you downloaded). If the installer doesn't recognize your JAVA_HOME, follow the instructions here.
NOTE: wls12213 (or something else starting with wls) is your ORACLE_HOME. ORACLE_HOME by default is placed wherever you install WebLogic.
Travel to ORACLE_HOME\oracle_common\common\bin and run config.cmd.
During the installation, take note of the default domain location (which will be something like C:\wls12213\user_projects\domains\base_domain), the admin name and password, and admin server URL.

Install NetBeans

Once NetBeans is installed, add a new server under Services -> Servers -> Add Server. Choose WebLogic when prompted. Select your ORACLE_HOME directory as the server location.

Install Oracle Database

Take note of your Global Database name, username, password, and pluggable database name. Note: if the path name is too long, uncheck the box in the upper right hand corner, as seen in this answer. Log into https://localhost:5500/em/login as sys (check as sysdba) and whatever password you specified during installation. If this doesn't work, open SQL Plus, enter username sys as SYSDBA and the password you specified during installation.

Download Oracle SQL Developer

This doesn't need to be installed.

Welcome!

Instant Coffee is a short tutorial designed to help you get started with Java EE web development, using WebLogic Server, Oracle Database 12c, Java ServerFaces and a handful of libraries.

Background

Several experiences in particular motivated me to pursue this project. When I was assigned to work on Campbell Online, a web-based dictionary of painters for the Museum of the White Mountains, I had to learn Java EE from scratch and would have appreciated a beginner-level introduction to it. In my exploration of various web frameworks, I came across a number of easy-to-follow demo applications, in particular the Symfony Demo App - a small CRUD app that allowed the user to view the code behind each page - but found no similar example for Java EE. Certainly, demo applications exist, but all of them are hulking, enterprise-scale beasts that no beginner would be comfortable taking on. I was inspired to create a similar small, easy-to-understand application in Java EE. Lastly, I was motivated to create some sort of enduring record of what I learned during my time at Plymouth State Applications and Development. As my office moves away from Java EE and to different frameworks, I feared that the knowledge I gained might be lost, and that incoming interns might miss out on a rewarding opportunity to learn a valuable and marketable skill. It is my hope that this app might serve as a small repository of my knowledge of Java EE, and might inspire future interns and students to consider pursuing projects in this underutilized, but powerful web stack.